### Sebastien VARRETTE, PhD

### Research Associate, Doctor in Computer Science,

specialized in Distributed Platforms Security and HPC systems.

Phone: +33(0)6 74 57 90 05 E-mail: Sebastien.Varrette@uni.lu Home page: http://varrette.gforge.uni.lu

Born on November 27th, 1979 (in France) Married (2004), two children (2007,2010)

ENGINEER EXPERTISE: High Performance Computing (HPC), Grid & Cluster Platforms.

I'm administrating cluster-based HPC systems since 2003 (Linux environment)

Keywords: HPC, Debian, Xen, Puppet, OpenLDAP, git

MAIN RESEARCH DOMAINS: Security and Evaluation of Distributed Computing Platforms (clusters, grids or clouds).

Relevant contributions in which I'm involved:

- $\bullet$  Code Obfuscation  $% \left( 1\right) =\left( 1\right) =\left( 1\right) +\left( 1\right) +\left( 1\right) =\left( 1\right) +\left( 1\right) +\left( 1\right) =\left( 1\right) +\left( 1\right$
- Crash/cheating faults analysis in grid platforms
- Performance evaluation & Energy efficiency of HPC/Cloud platforms
- $\bullet$  Design of the authentication system of Grid 5000
- Developing security awareness by education

#### Education

2007	Ph.D. In Computer Science, University of Luxembourg (UL) & Institut National Polyto Thesis: Security in Large Scale Distributed Systems: Au Advisors: Franck Leprévost (UL) & Jean-Louis Roch (III)	uthentication and Result Checking
2003	M.Sc. in Computer Science	with honours $(TB/First\ Class)$
	Speciality: Cryptology, Security and Information Coding (	
	Institut National Polytechnique de Grenoble (INPG) & Un	niversity Joseph Fourier (UJF)
2003	Master's Degree in Engineering (Telecoms ENSIMA	(G) with honours $(B/2.1)$
	Speciality: Computer Sciences and Telecommunications	rank: top $10\%$
1997 - 2000	Advanced Mathematics and Physics studies	
	For the competitive entrance to the French engineering	schools
1997	SCIENTIFIC "BACCALAURÉAT" (French "A" levels)	with honours $(B/2.1)$

#### **Employment**

2011 - now	Research Associate (UL, Luxembourg)
2007 - 2010	SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR (UL, Luxembourg)
2004 - 2007	Research Assistant (UL, Luxembourg)
2003	System administrator (ID-IMAG, Grenoble, France)

### Teaching Experience

2008 - now	Parallel & Grid Computing, Middleware	Master MICS2 (UL)
2004 - 2007	Programming Techniques I	Bachelor I1/CUT1 (UL)
	Advanced Programming in C, C++ and Java	Bachelor I2 (UL)
	System Administration and Network Security	Master CSCI2 (UJF)
2006	CRYPTOLOGY AND NETWORK SECURITY	
	Master in Computer Science (Univ. of Yaoundé I. Cameroon)	

### Additional Information

Languages	French (native language), English (fluent) and German (basic knowledge)
Sports	Karate (Black belt – 2nd DAN, Federal Instructor Diploma (DIF)), Jogging, Badminton, Ski etc.

# ${\bf Graduate\ Students\ Supervision}$

PhD.	Jakub Muszyński (2011 –) Benoît Bertholon (2010 –)	Integrity aspects on grid and cloud platforms Confidentiality & Integrity Issues over Cloud Computing Platforms
Master	Anna Giannakou (2013 –) Valentin Plugaru (2012 –) Fotis Georgatos (2012 – ) Mateusz Guzek (2011) Benoît Bertholon (2009) Christophe Weis (2009) Dominic Dunlop (2008 – 2009)	9
Bachelor	Romain Cavagna (2007 – 2008)  Hyacinthe Cartiaux (2011 – )  Bernard Reichert (2008)	

# Research Projects

2011 - 2013	UL EVOPERF (UL contribution: 373 k€)
2010 - 2012	FNR CORE GreenIT (Total: 1,5 M€, FNR contribution: 432 k€)
2010 - 2012	AFR PhD Bertholon (PHD-09-142; Scientific Advisor; Total/AFR contribution: 110 k€)
	Confidentiality and Integrity Issues over Cloud Computing Platforms
2009 - 2013	EU COST ACTION IC0804: Energy efficiency in large scale distributed systems
2009 - 2013	EU CoreGrid
2006 - 2008	ANR SAFESCALE-BGPR (ANR-05-SSIA-0005; ANR contribution: 68 k€)
2005 - now	GRID'5000 (technical committee)
2005 - 2007	FNR-SECOM TESEGRAD (FNR contribution: 300 k€)
2004 - 2007	CRYPTALPES
2004 - 2006	RAGTIME (Total: 545 k€, Rhône-Alpes Region contribution: 217 k€)

### **Professional Development**

2009 – now	TECHNICAL ADVISOR for LCSB and the MECO Ministry on HPC projects	
2007 - now	now UL HPC MANAGER. The current platform consists in:	
	151 computing nodes, 1556 cores, $R_{\text{peak}} = 14,245 \text{ TFlops}$	
	59 servers (74,6% are Xen VMs)	
	NFS and Lustre Storage (Total raw capacity: 511TB)	
2006	EGIDE mission for 3 weeks in Cameroon (master lecture – Univ. of Yaoudé I)	
2005	EDITORIAL COMMITTEE for the definition of new UL master and bachelor degrees	
2005 - 2006	EDITORIAL COMMITTEE, UL website (CMS selection & management)	
2005 - 2006	FACULTY COUNCIL, elected member (assistant representative)	
2000 - 2002	Ensimag Junior Enterprise, developer member	
	·	

# Participation to the research community

Membership	IEEE Computer and Computational Intelligence society		
Events	General (co-)chair: LPWST 2010 (Luxembourg)		
	Program or Organizational Chair:		
	OPTIM 2011 (Istanbul, Turkey), SCALSOL 2011 (Pafos, Cyprus), OPTIM 2010 (Caen, France)		
	International Program Committee Member:		
	PCGrid 2011 (Anchorage, USA), PCGrid 2010 (Melbourne, Australia)		
Reviews	JOURNAL REVIEWER: FGCS (Elsevier), J. of Supercomputing (Springer), JPDC (Elsevier), PARCO		
	(Elsevier), IJFCS (WO), TPDS (IEEE)		
	International Conference reviews (in addition to the above elements & events):		
	EuroPar 2011 (Bordeaux, France), SiiS 2011 (Warsaw, Poland), MENS 2010 (Miami, USA) NAS		
	2010 (Macau, China) HPCS 2008 (Cyprus), MCO'08 (Metz, France) PSAI 2008 (Barcelona, Spain)		
	GPC 2007 (Paris, France), HICSS-38 (Hawaii, USA)		

Publication category	Quantity
PhD Thesis	1
Books	3
Magazine	1
Book Chapters	7
International journals	4
International conferences with proceedings and reviews	26
(French) national conferences with proceedings and reviews	4
International conferences with proceedings	1
International conferences with reviews	6
Masters Thesis	1
Technical Reports	8
Miscellaneous	1
Total:	63

		Citations:149,Years:11			
or Perish	Cites/year: 13.55	Cites/paper: $3.10/2.0/0$	Cites/author: 58.98	Papers/author: 20.25	Query date: <b>2013-05-20</b>

#### Selected Publications

- [1] S. Varrette. Sécurité des Architectures de Calcul Distribué: Authentification et Certification de Résultats. PhD thesis, INP Grenoble and Université du Luxembourg, Sept. 2007. In French.
- [2] J.-G. Dumas, J.-L. Roch, E. Tannier, and S. Varrette. *Théorie des Codes : Compression, Cryptage et Correction*. Collection Sciences Sup. Dunod, Mars 2007. 352 pages, in French.
- [3] J. Muszyński, S. Varrette, P. Bouvry, F. Seredyński, and S. U. Khan. Convergence Analysis of Evolutionary Algorithms in the Presence of Crash-Faults and Cheaters. *Intl. Journal. of Computers and Mathematics with Applications* (CAMWA), 64(12):3805–3819, Dec 2012.
- [4] J. Muszynski, S. Varrette, and P. Bouvry. Expected Running Time of Parallel Evolutionary Algorithms on Unimodal Pseudo-Boolean Functions over Small-World Networks. In *Proc. of the IEEE Congress on Evolutionary Computation (CEC'2013)*, Cancún, Mexico, June 2013. IEEE.
- [5] M. Jarus, S. Varrette, A. Oleksiak, and P. Bouvry. Performance Evaluation and Energy Efficiency of High-Density HPC Platforms Based on Intel, AMD and ARM Processors. In *Proc. of the Intl. Conf. on Energy Efficiency in Large Scale Distributed Systems (EE-LSDS'13)*, LNCS, Vienna, Austria, Apr 2013. Springer Verlag.
- [6] B. Bertholon, S. Varrette, and P. Bouvry. CertiCloud: a Novel TPM-based Approach to Ensure Cloud IaaS Security. In Proc. of the 4th IEEE Intl. Conf. on Cloud Computing (CLOUD 2011), Washington DC, USA, July 4–9 2011. IEEE Computer Society.
- [7] D. Dunlop, S. Varrette, and P. Bouvry. Deskilling HPL Using an Evolutionary Algorithm to Automate Cluster Benchmarking. In *Proc. of 8th Intl. Conf. on Parallel Processing and Applied Mathematics Part II (PPAM 2009)*, volume 6068 of *LNCS*, pages 102–114, Wroclaw, Poland, Sept. 13–16 2009. Springer Verlag. Publication appeared in 2010.
- [8] J.-L. Roch and S. Varrette. Probabilistic Certification of Divide & Conquer Algorithms on Global Computing Platforms. Application to Fault-Tolerant Exact Matrix-Vector Product. In *Proc. of the ACM Intl. Workshop on* Parallel Symbolic Computation'07 (PASCO'07), pages 88–92, London, Ontario, Canada, July 27–28 2007. ACM.
- [9] S. Varrette, S. Georget, J. Montagnat, J.-L. Roch, and F. Leprevost. Distributed Authentication in GRID5000. In *Proc. of OTM Confederated Int. Workshops on Grid Computing and its Application to Data Analysis (GADA'05)*, volume 3762 of *LNCS*, pages 314–326, Agia Napa, Cyprus, Nov. 1 2005. Springer Verlag.
- [10] A.Krings, J.-L. Roch, S. Jafar, and S. Varrette. A Probabilistic Approach for Task and Result Certification of Large-scale Distributed Applications in Hostile Environments. In *Proc. of the European Grid Conference (EGC2005)*, volume 3470 of *LNCS*, pages 323–333, Amsterdam, Netherlands, Feb. 14–16 2005. Springer Verlag.